<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bull of Pope Alexander VIII. Published two days before his death. Annulling all the proceedings of the French clergy, assembled at Paris, 1682 Published by authority.</title>
            <author>Alexander VIII, Pope, 1610-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230811</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896555</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896555</idno>
            <idno type="VID">134531</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76033)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 134531)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2415:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bull of Pope Alexander VIII. Published two days before his death. Annulling all the proceedings of the French clergy, assembled at Paris, 1682 Published by authority.</title>
                  <author>Alexander VIII, Pope, 1610-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. Jones in the Savoy,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690 [i.e. 1691]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>In double columns.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and actual date of publication from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Wing reports date of publication as 1690[1].</note>
                  <note>In both English and Latin.</note>
                  <note>The Latin part has caption title: Alexander Papa VIII.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  France --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  France --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
            <pb facs="tcp:134531:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:134531:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE BULL OF Pope Alexander VIII. Publiſhed Two days before his Death. Annulling all the Proceedings of the FRENCH CLERGY, Aſſembled at <hi>PARIS,</hi> 1682.</head>
            <head type="sub"> 
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi> 
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>ALEXANDER VIII. Pope.</signed>
            </opener>
            <opener>
               <hi>In the Name of God,</hi> Amen.</opener>
            <p>KNow all men by theſe Preſents, That in the Year of our Lord Chriſt 1691. Indiction the 14th, <hi>January</hi> the 31th, and in the ſecond Year of the Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate of our moſt Holy Father in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> our Lord Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 8th: I, deputed <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial,</hi> whoſe name is Subſcribed, did ſee and read ſome Letters, ſeal'd with the Seal of the <hi>Fiſher,</hi> after the manner of the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> which ſaid Letters were neither blotted, vitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor interlin'd, and were of the Tenor, following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALEXANDER</hi> VIII, Pope. For the perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Memory of the Thing. Amongſt the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Cares of our Paſtoral Office, with which we are perpetually exerciſed; This One, hath a peculiar Influence upon us <hi>viz.</hi> That we may preſerve and maintain the Rights of the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick See, and of the Univerſal Church; and alſo the Privileges of each particular Church, Holy Places, and Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, every where entire and inviolate againſt whatſoever Aſſaults may be made againſt them to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringement; and to vindicate them from all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury and damage, according to the Power com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to us by God, by ſuch ways and means as, after due and mature, conſideration, we ſhall judge in the Lord to be agreeable to Juſtice and Reaſon. Since then it hath pleaſed the moſt High; by the inſcrutable Myſtery of his Divine Providence, to raiſe Us, how unworthy ſoever, to the Higheſt Dignity in the Church Militant; Before all other Buſineſſes, which have offered themſelves to our Pontifical Care, Thoſe have moſt ſorely and grievouſly afflicted Us, (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Bowels of Love which We bear to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our dearly Beloved Son in Chriſt, <hi>Lewis</hi> the moſt Chriſtian King, and his moſt flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi>) which have been acted in that Kingdom, either againſt the Rights of the Churches thereof, or againſt the Authority of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of the Univerſal Church. For ſome Venerable Brethren Arch-Biſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and other Eccleſiaſtical Perſons of that Kingdom in an Aſſembly of the <hi>Gallican Clergy,</hi> held at <hi>Paris, Anno D.</hi> 1682<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> upon the Account of Extending the Right of that which they call the <hi>Regalia,</hi> over all the Churches of the ſaid Kingdom, to which they gave their Aſſent, have acted things very grievous and bitter to Us; as alſo by publiſhing a Declaration thereupon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Power,</hi> containing Four Propoſitions; and beſides after. That Aſſembly, there followed prejudicial Mandates, Arreſts, Confirmations, Epiſtles, Edicts, and Decrees whatſoever they be, publiſhed by any Perſons, either Eccleſiaſtick or Laick, in any Office or Authority whatſoever; Beſides many things of late years having been any other way acted in that Kingdom, prejudicial to the Apoſtolick See, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church or to any other Churches, Monaſteries and Holy Places, their Perſons, Eſtates, Goods and Rights, reſpectively; or any otherways to the Detriment of the Juriſdiction, Immunity and Liberty Eccleſiaſtical. We, whom God hath appointed upon Earth to be the Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:134531:2"/> of Eccleſiaſtical Rights, Day and Night in the bitterneſs of our Soul, have had ſerious Thoughts of theſe Things, and lifting up our hands to the Lord with Tears and Groans, have ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly prayed him from the bottom of our heart, That he would aſſiſt Us by his powerful Grace, That We might rightfully Execute this difficult part of the Apoſtolical Office, committed to Us. Upon which Conſideration, as alſo that We might give a good Account of our Stewardſhip to the Supreme Judge, and might not be charged with Negligence in the Adminiſtration of our Office, (as far as God of his Goodneſs hath enabled Us) We have hitherto left no Means unattempted, whereby We might cauſe the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of ſuch prejudicial Grievances aforeſaid, ſeriouſly to retract what they had done. And to the intent, that We might more effectually, and fully make Proviſion for the Indemnity of the See aforeſaid, of the Univerſal Church, of the Juriſdiction, Immunity and Liberty Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal of Churches, Monaſteries, and Places of Devotion, and of the foreſaid Perſons therein, for all times to come; having heard the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of many of our Venerable Brethren, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the Roman Church, and other Gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates in Theology, who were ſpecially choſen by Us to examine the Decrees of the Doctors in this Buſineſs, They having maturely diſcuſs'd the Point, and laid it all before Us, out of the Deſire, as far as God ſhall enable Us, to Remedy the foreſaid Inconveniences; And alſo calling to mind the Carriage of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 11th of Happy Memory; who in way of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſome Letters, which the Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, and other Eccleſiaſtical Perſons aforeſaid wrote to him, to acquaint him with what they had done in that Kingdom; He by his Letters inform of a <hi>Breve,</hi> dated the 11th of <hi>April,</hi> 1682. did Condemn, Reſcind and Vacate all that was done in the ſaid Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, in the Buſineſs of the <hi>Regalia,</hi> with whatſoever followed thereupon, or what might be hereafter Attempted to that purpoſe: Theſe he declared to be utterly Null and Void. We therefore treading in his Steps, having conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered what was Acted in the Aſſembly afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, <hi>Anno D.</hi> 1682. As well concerning the Extending the Rights of the <hi>Regalia,</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Declaration of the Eccleſiaſtical Power of ſuch Acts; as alſo of all and ſingular Mandates, Arreſts, Confirmations, Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Epiſtles, Edicts, Decrees given forth or publiſhed by Authority, either Eccleſiaſtical or Lay: And alſo of all other the Grievances aforeſaid in the ſaid Kingdom Acted and done by whomſoever, or for whatſoever Cauſe, and whatever Manner; as alſo of whatſoever fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed thereupon, Having a ſpecial and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Regard to the Tenor of what was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Acted; and thoſe Memoirs being faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and ſufficiently Copyed and Expreſſed Word for Word; By our own mere Motion, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Knowledge and mature Deliberation, out of the Fulneſs of our Apoſtolical Power, all and ſingular Things acted and done in the aforeſaid Aſſembly of the Gallican Clergy, in the Year 1682. as well concerning the Extent of the Right of the <hi>Regalia,</hi> as concerning the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their Eccleſiaſtical Power, and the Four Propoſitions contained therein: Together with all and ſingular Mandates, Arreſts, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmations, Declarations, Epiſtles, Edicts; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees given forth or publiſhed by any Perſons either Eccleſiaſtical or Lay, however Qualified, enjoying any Authority or Power requiring particular Mention; and alſo all other things, how many, or whatſoever, any ways prejudicial to the ſaid Apoſtolick See; and to either the Juriſdiction, Immunity or Eccleſiaſtical Dignity of the Roman Church, or otherwiſe to Churches, Monaſteries and Holy Places aforeſaid; and the Perſons, Eſtates, Goods, Priviledges, Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives and Rights whatſoever belonging to the Perſons therein Reſpectively, which have been Acted in that Kingdom, with all in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and every thing in particular, whenſoever or howſoever following thereupon, or which may follow thereupon at any time hereafter. We by the Tenour of theſe Preſents, do De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and Decree, That they are all Null and Void, invalid, and of no Force or Effect; and that they were ſo from the very beginning, are ſo, and for ever will be ſo; And that no Man is bound to obſerve them, or any of them, tho' he hath taken an Oath ſo to do: And that no Man hath had, or hath at preſent any Right Action or Colour of Title of Poſſeſſion, or cauſe of Preſcription for Poſſeſſion, for a long time paſt and immemorial, tho' no Diſturbance or Interruption hath followed, or ſhould follow; And leſs Title can accrue thereby for time to come. Neither have they made, or do they make any right Settlement, but are ſo to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted and taken, as if they had been never done nor extant. And yet nevertheleſs to ſhew our abundant Caution, as there is need, tho' by our mere Motion, Knowledge, Deliberation and Plenitude of Power, We Diſown, Abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, make Void and Null the Acts and Deeds, and all the Premiſſes aforeſaid, and do Vacate them, as altogether without any Force or Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; and do Proteſt before God concerning their Nullity, Decreing theſe preſent Letters, and whatſoever is contained in them, to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Firm and Good, notwithſtanding that ſome having an Intereſt in the Premiſſes, tho' worthy of ſpecial and particular Mention, did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereto, nor were Called, Cited and Heard; Nor the Cauſes for which theſe Preſents were given forth, were ſufficiently produced, verified, or any ways juſtified; or for any other Cauſe whatſoever, Colour, Pretence, and Head, even in the cloſe Body of the Law, at no time up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Account of Surreptitiouſneſs, Stealth or Nullity, or Invalidity, or Miſtake of our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, or the Conſent of thoſe who have an Intereſt, or pretend to have an Intereſt, or any other defect whatſoever, tho' great, unthought of, or which could never be thought of, or from any other Head, drawn from Law, Fact, Statute, Cuſtom or Priviledge; notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:134531:2"/> all which, theſe Preſents ought not be Queſtioned, Impugned, Invalidated, Retracted, called into controverſy, or be reduced to terms of Law; but are, and are to be, valid and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious for ever; and ought to have and obtain their full and entire effect, and be inviolably obſerved by all and every one to whom it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, or at any time hereafter ſhall belong. Thus and no otherwiſe, in all and ſingular the Premiſes, all ordinary Judges whatſoever, the Auditors of Cauſes of the Apoſtolick Chamber, the Cardinals of the Sacred <hi>Roman</hi> Church, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Legats <hi>de Latere,</hi> and the Nuncio's of the foreſaid Apoſtolick See, or any other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, enjoying or which may hereafter enjoy any Eminent Place or Dignity, are to judge and determine, We taking away from them, and from every one of them all Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to judge, declare, and interpret any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways; and if any one ſhall attempt, either know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly or ignorantly, to judge otherwiſe of theſe Preſents; by any Authority whatſoever, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it to be Null and Void; notwithſtanding the premiſes, the Apoſtolick Conſtitutions and Ordinances made in General or Provincial Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, and Synods either General or Special; and, as far as need is, our Rule and the Rule of the Apoſtolick Chamber of not abridging any Man's Right; as alſo the Imperial and Municipal Laws, and alſo all Statutes, ſtrengthned by Oath, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Confirmation, or any other Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Cuſtom even time out of mind, as alſo Privileges, Indulgences, Conceſſions, granted by Letters Apoſtolick to any Places or Perſons, tho' Crowned Heads, or eminent for any other Dignity, either Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified any other way, or requiring Special No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations under whatſoever Tenor or Forms of Word, and with what Derogatory Clauſes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever and other more efficacious and unuſual Clauſes and Decrees, even like to Thoſe made by our mere Motion, certain Knowledge, and Fulneſs of Power, tho' Conſiſtorially or any otherways, Granted, Publiſhed, Made, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times iterated, and at divers Seaſons approved, confirmed, and renewed, to the Contrary; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all and every of which, tho' for their ſufficient derogation a ſpecial, expreſs and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular mention ought to be made of them and their Contents, Word for Word, and not in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Clauſes importing the ſame thing; or if any other Expreſſion were to be made, or other exquiſite Form to be kept, yet we accounting thoſe Tenors to be fully and ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by theſe Preſents, as if they had been inſerted Word for Word, and judging the Form delivered in them to be obſerved, we do ſpecially and expreſly derogate them, as to the effect of the Premiſſes; and our Will is, that they be derogated, any other thing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hereof notwithſtanding. Our Pleaſure alſo is, that the ſame Credit is to be given in all Places and in all Nations, both in Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and out of them to the Tranſcripts or Copies of theſe preſent Letters, Subſcribed by the hand of ſome Notary, and Sealed with the Seal of ſome Perſon in Eccleſiaſtical Dignity, as if the <hi>Breve</hi> it ſelf had been ſhewn, to be Read by them. Given at <hi>Rome</hi> in St. <hi>Marys</hi> the Greater, under the Seal of the <hi>Fiſher,</hi> the 4th Day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1690. and of our Popedom, the firſt. <hi>J. F.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Alban.</hi> In the Place + of the Seal of the <hi>Fiſher.</hi> Upon which Letters, I, Publick Notary, whoſe name is Subſcribed, have made this preſent publick Inſtrument and Tranſcript, that it might be ſtood to, and firmly believed, both in Courts of Juſtice, and without. Given at <hi>Rome,</hi> as above, in the preſence alſo of D. <hi>John Baptiſta Rigantes,</hi> and of <hi>Erneſtus Ziglinus,</hi> who were called to witneſs the Premiſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>In the Place <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> of the Seal.
<list>
                     <item>B. Cardinal, <hi>Datary.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>J. F.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Alban.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>The Pre-inſerted Apoſtolick Letters being compared with the Original, do agree there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Joſeph Paulutius,</hi> Official deputed.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <postscript>
               <p>'Tis ſo,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Witneſs <hi>Seraphinus Crucianus,</hi> depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Notary of the Apoſtolick Chamber. In the Place <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> of the Signe.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:134531:3"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>ALEXANDER Papa VIII.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>IN nomine Domini Amen. Cunctis ubique pateat, &amp; ſit notum, quòd Anno a Nativitate Domini Noſtri Jeſu Chriſti Milleſimo Sexcenteſimo Nonageſimo pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, Indictione xiiij., Die verò trigeſima prima Januarii, Pontificatûs autem SS. in Chriſto Patris &amp; Domini Noſtri Domini ALEXANDRI PP. VIII. Anno ejus ſecundo: Ego infraſcriptus Officialis deputatus vidi, &amp; legi quaſdam Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teras ſub Annulo Piſcatoris more Romanae Curiae expeditas ſanas, integras, &amp; non vitiatas tenoris qui ſequitur ult. ALEXANDER PP. VIII. Ad Perpetuam rei memoriam.</p>
            <p>Inter multiplices Paſtoralis Officii Noſtri curas, quibus jugiter premimur, in illam peculiari ſtudio incumbimus, ut Apoſtolicae Sedis, ac univerſalis Eccleſiae, nec non etiam ſingularum Eccleſiarum, Locorumque Piorum, ac Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Eccleſiaſticarum Jura ubique farta, tecta, ac illibata tueri, &amp; conſervare, eaque adverſus quaecunque, per quae illis aliquid detrimenti in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferri poſſet, tradita nobis divinitùs Poteſtate vindicare ſatagamus, ſicut omnibus maturè ac debitè penſatis Juſtitiae, ac rationi conſentaneum eſſe in Domino arbitramur Cùm itaque ex quo primùm humilitatem noſtram inſcrutabili Divinae ſuae Providentiae arcano in ſuprema mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litantis Eccleſiae ſpecula collocavit Altiſſimus, prae caeteris, quae Pontificiae Noſtrae ſollicitudini ſe ſe obtulere, negotiis, illa in primis graviſſima ac nobis, qui Chariſſimum in Chriſto Filium noſtrum Ludovicum Francorum Regem Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſimum, ac florentiſſimum illius Regnum in viſceribus gerimus charitatis, permoleſta &amp; planè acerba acciderint, quae ſive adverſus dicti Regni Eccleſiarum Jura, ſive adverſus Romani Pontificis, &amp; Eccleſiae Univerſae authoritatem nonnullis Venerabiles Fratres Archiepiſcopi, Epiſcopi, &amp; alii ejuſdem Regni Eccleſiaſtici Viri in Comitiis Cleri Gallicani Pariſiis Anno M.DC.LXXXII congregati tum praeſtito inibi per eos extenſioni illius Juris quod vocant Regaliae ad omnes dicti Regni Eccleſias aſſenſu, tum editâ ſubinde de Poteſtate Eccleſiaſtica quatuor propoſitiones continente declaratione, peregerunt, quaeque ipſa Comitia ſubſequuta fuerunt Mandata, Arreſta, Confirmationes, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarationes, Epiſtolae, Edicta, &amp; Decreta, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque à quibuſvis Perſonis, ſive Eccleſiaſticis, ſive Laicis quavis authoritate, &amp; poteſtate fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentibus edita, ſeu publicata, nec non quae aliàs demùm nonnullis abhinc annis, in Regno prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fato eidem Sedi Apoſtolicae, Romanaeque Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, ſeu quibuſcunque aliis Eccleſiis, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteriis, &amp; Locis Piis, illorumque reſpectivè Perſonis, Rebus, Bonis, &amp; Juribus, ſeu aliàs Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictioni, vel Immunitati, aut libertati Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticae, quomodolibet praejudicialia quovis modo peracta ac geſta fuerunt: haec Nos, qui Jurium Eccleſiaſticorum Aſſertores in Terris à Domino conſtituti ſumus, dies, nocteſque in amaritudine Animae noſtrae cogitantes, manus noſtras cum lachrymis, &amp; ſuſpiriis levavimus ad Dominum, eumque toto Cordis affectu ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gavimus, ut Nobis potenti gratiae ſuae auxilio adeſſet, quò ardua hac in re commiſſi nobis Apoſtolici muneris partes ſalubriter exequi va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leremus. Eaque conſideratione adducti, ac nè Supremo Judici rationem villicationis noſtrae red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dituri negligentiae in credita Nobis adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione argueremur (quantum Divina Bonitas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit) nihil hucuſque praetermiſimus, quo praeju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicialia praefata ab iiſmet, qui eam peregerant, ex animo retractarentur. Verùm quò effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciùs, ac uberiùs Sedis praefatae Eccleſiae Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſae, Juriſdictioniſque &amp; Immunitatis, ac Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatis Eccleſiaſticae, Eccleſiarumque, Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riorum, &amp; Locorum Piorum hujuſmodi, illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque Perſonarum praefatarum indemnitate perpetuis futuris temporibus conſultum ſit, audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quàm plurium ex Venerabilibus Fratribus Noſtris S. R. E. Cardinalibus, &amp; nonnullorum in Sacra Theologia Magiſtrorum, ac etiam in Decretis Doctorum ad examen negocii hujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi à Nobis ſpecialiter delectorum, qui illud maturè diſcuſſerunt, remque totam nobis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſuerunt, ſententiis, quantum Nobis ex Alto conceditur, providere volentes, ac fel. rec. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentii PP. XI. Praedeceſſoris noſtri, qui occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione reſcribendi ad Litteras, quibus Archiepiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:134531:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> Epiſcopi, &amp; alii Eccleſiaſtici Viri ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pradicti, de rebus ab ipſis geſtis certiorem eum reddiderant, per quaſdam ſuas in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mili forma Brevis die 11. Aprilis M.DC.LXXXII. expeditas Litteras im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probavit, reſcidit, &amp; caſſavit, quae in del. Comitiis acta fuerunt in negotio Regaliae cum omnibus inde ſequutis, &amp; quae ſubinde attentari contigiſſet, eaque perpetuo irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, &amp; inania declaravit, veſtigiis inhaeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, nec non in dictis Comitiis Anni M.DC.LXXXII. tam circa extenſionem Juris Regaliae, quam circa declarationem de Poteſtate Eccleſiaſtica hujuſmodi acto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ac etiam omnium, &amp; ſingulorum Mandatorum, Arreſtorum, Confirmatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, Declarationum, Epiſtolarum, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictorum, Decretorum quavis authoritate ſive Eccleſiaſticâ, ſive etiam Laicali edito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſeu publicatorum, nec non aliorum quomodolibet praejudicialium praefatorum in Regno ſupradicto quandocumque, &amp; à quibuſvis, ac ex quacunque cauſa, &amp; quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis modo factorum, &amp; geſtorum, ac inde ſequutorum quorumcunque etiam ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, &amp; individuam mentionem, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſionem de neceſſitate requirentium te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nores, &amp; datas etiam veriores praeſentibus pro plenè, &amp; ſufficienter expreſſis, ac de verbo ad verbum inſertis, &amp; exactiſſimè ſpecificatis habentes Motu proprio, ac ex certa ſcientia, &amp; matura deliberatione noſtris, deque Apoſtolicae poteſtatis ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudine omnia, &amp; ſingula quae tam quoad extenſionem Juris Regaliae, quàm quoad declarationem de Poteſtate Eccleſiaſtica, ac quatuor in ea contentas propoſitiones in ſupradictis Comitiis Cleri Gallicani Anno M.DC.LXXXII. habitis acta, &amp; geſta fuerunt cum omnibus, &amp; ſingulis Mandatis, Arreſtis, Confirmationibus, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarationibus, Epiſtolis, Edictis, Decretis à quibuſvis Perſonis ſive Eccleſiaſticis, ſive Laicis quomodolibet qualificatis, quavis authoritate, &amp; Poteſtate, etiam individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am expreſſionem requirente, fungentibus, editis, ſeu publicatis, nec non reliqua omnia quotcumque, &amp; qualiacumque eidem Sedi Apoſtolicae, Romanaeque Eccleſiae vel Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictioni, Immunitati, vel Libertati Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticae, ſeu aliàs Eccleſiis, Monaſteriis, &amp; Locis piis praefatis, illorumque reſpectivè perſonis Rebus, Bonis, Privilegiis, praerogativis, &amp; Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus quibuſcunque quomodolibet praejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialia in dicto Regno peracta, &amp; geſta cum omnibus, &amp; ſingulis quandocunque, &amp; quomodocunque inde ſequutis, &amp; quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque tempore ſequuturis, ipſo jure nulla, irrita, invalida, inania, viribusque, &amp; effectu penitùs, &amp; omninò vacua ab ipſo initio fuiſſe, &amp; eſſe, ac perpetuo fore, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minemque ad illorum, ſeu cujuslibet eorum, etiamſi juramento vallata ſint, obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam teneri, neque ex illis cuiquam aliquod jus, vel actionem, aut titulum etiam colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum, vel poſſidendi, aut praeſcribendi cauſam, etiamſi longiſſimi, &amp; immemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis temporis poſſeſſio, etiam citr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ullam interpellationem, vel interruptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſubſequnta ſit, vel ſubſequatur, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitum fuiſſe, nec eſſe, minusque ullo tempore acquiri, &amp; competere poſſe, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que illa ullum ſtatum facere, vel ſeciſſe, ſed perindè ac ſi nunquam emanaſſent, vel facta fuiſſent, pro non extantibus, &amp; non factis perpetuo haberi debere tenore praeſentium declaramus, &amp; decernimus. Et nihilominus ad abundantiorem caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, &amp; quatenus opus ſit, acta, &amp; geſta praefata aliaque praemiſſa omnia, Motu, ſcientia, deliberatione, &amp; poteſtatis ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudine paribus improbamus, caſſamus, irritamus, &amp; annullamus, viribuſque, &amp; effectu penitus, &amp; omnino vacuamus, &amp; contra illa, deque eorum nullitate coram DEO proteſtamur. Decernentes eaſdem praeſentes Litteras, &amp; in eis contenta quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque etiam ex eo quod quicumque in praemiſſis intereſſe habentes etiam ſpecifica, &amp; individua mentione digni, illis non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſerint, nec ad eo vocati, citati, &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti, neque cauſae propter quas eaedem praeſentes emanarint, ſufficienter adductae, verificatae, aut ullo modo juſtificatae fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, aut ex alia quacumque cauſa, colore, praetextu, &amp; capite, etiam in Corpore Juris clau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nullo unquam tempore de ſubreptionis, vel obreptionis, aut nullitatis, vel invaliditatis vitio, ſeu intentionis noſtrae, aut intereſſe habenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, vel habere praetendentium conſenſus, aliove quocum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> etiam quamtumlibet mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, ac incogitato, inexcogitabilique defectu, aut ex alio quovis capite à Jure, vel Facto, aut Statuto, Conſuetudine, vel Privilegio reſultante notari, impugnari, invalidari, retractari, in controverſiam vocari, ſeu ad terminos Juris reduci ullatenus poſſe, ſed ipſas praeſentes Litteras ſemper &amp; perpetuo firmas, validas, &amp; efficaces exiſtere, &amp; fore, ſuoſque plenarios, &amp; integros effectus ſortiri, &amp; obtinere, ac ab omnibus, &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis, ad quos ſpectat, &amp; pro tempore quandocumque ſpectabit, inviolabiliter ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervari. Sicque &amp; non aliter in praemiſſis omnibus, &amp; ſingulis per quoſcumque Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices ordinarios, &amp; delagatos etiam Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarum Sac. Palatii Apoſtolici Auditores, ac
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:134531:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> Sac. R. E. Cardinales etiam de Latere Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatos, &amp; Sedis Apoſtolicae praefatae Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cios, alioſve quoſlibet quacumque praee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minentia, &amp; poteſtate fungentes, &amp; functu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros, ſublatâ eis, &amp; eorum cuilibet quavis aliter judicandi, declarandi, &amp; interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandi facultate, &amp; authoritate ſemper, &amp; ubique judicari, &amp; definiri debere, ac irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; inane ſi ſecus ſuper his à quoquam quavis auctoritate ſcienter. vel ignoranter contigerit attentari; non obſtantibus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſis, ac Apoſtolicis, &amp; in Univerſalibus, provincialibuſque, &amp; Synodalibus Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis editis generalibus, vel ſpecialibus Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutionibus, &amp; Ordinationibus, &amp; quate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus opus ſit, noſtrâ &amp; Cancellariae Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae regula de Jure quaeſito non tollendo, legibus quoque etiam Imperialibus, &amp; mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicipalibus, nec non quibuſvis etiam Jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento, Confirmatione Apoſtolica, vel quavis firmentate alia roboratis Statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp; Conſuetudinibus etiam imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morabilibus, Privilegiis quoque, Indultis, Conceſſionibus, &amp; Litteris Apoſtolicis quibuſcunque locis, &amp; Perſonis etiam Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gali, &amp; alia quavis ſive Eccleſiaſtica ſive Mundana Dignitate fulgentibus, &amp; alias quomodolibet qualificatis, ac ſpecialem expreſſionem requirentibus, ſub quibuſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que verborum tenoribus, &amp; formis, ac cum quibuſvis etiam derogatoriarum derogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis, aliiſque efficacioribus, &amp; inſolitis Clauſulis, &amp; Decretis etiam Motu, Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, &amp; poteſtatis plenitudine ſimilibus, ac Conſiſtorialiter, &amp; aliàs quomodolibet in contrarium praemiſſorum conceſſis, editis, factis, ac pluriès iteratis, &amp; quantiſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que vicibus approbatis, confirmatis, &amp; innovatis. Quibus omnibus &amp; ſingulis, etiamſi pro illorum ſufficienti derogatione de illis, eorumque totis tenoribus ſpecialis, ſpecifica expreſſa, &amp; individua, ac de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo ad verbum, non autem per Clauſulas generales idem importantes, mentio, ſeu quaevis alia expreſſio facienda, aut alia ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſita forma ad hoc ſervanda foret, teno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res hujuſmodi ac ſi de verbo ad verbum inſerti eſſent, praeſentibus pro plenè, &amp; ſufficienter expreſſis, &amp; inſertis, formani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que in illis traditam pro ſervata habentes, ad praemiſſorum effectum ſpecialiter, &amp; expreſsè derogamus, ac derogatum eſſe volumus, caeteriſque contrariis quibuſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que. Volumus autem, ut earundem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentium Litterarum tranſumptis, ſeu ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplis eam expreſſis manu alicujus Notarii ſubſcriptis, &amp; Sigillo Perſonae in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtica dignitate conſtitutae munitis, eadem prorſſus fides ubique Locorum, &amp; Gentium in Judicio, &amp; extra illud habeatur, quae ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beretur ipſis praeſentibus, ſi forent exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitae, vel oſtenſae. Datum Romae apud Sanctam Mariam Majorem ſub Annulo Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catoris die quarta Menſis Aug. M.DC.XC. Pontificatûs noſtri Anno Primo. J. F. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalis Albanus. Loco <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Annuli Piſcato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. Super quibus quidem Litteris Ego Notarius Publicus infraſcriptus hoc praeſens Publicum Tranſumpti Inſtrumentum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feci, ut eidem ſtetur, firmiterque credatur in Judicio, &amp; extra illud. Actum Romae ut ſuprà praeſentibus itidem DD. Joanne Baptiſta Rigante, &amp; Erneſto Ziglino ad praemiſſa vocatis, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Loco <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Sigilli.
<list>
                     <item>B. Cardinalis Prodatarius.</item>
                     <item>J. F. Cardinalis Albanus.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Praeinſertae Litterae Apoſtolicae cum ſuo Originali reviſae concordant.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Joſeph Paulutius Officialis deputatus.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <postscript>
               <p>Ità eſt.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Seraphinus Crucianus Cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lariae Apoſtolicae Notarius deputatus. Loco <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Signi.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed by <hi>Edw. Jones</hi> in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> 1690.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:134531:4"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
